SAMUEL MARTINEZ







6300 KESWICK PL. NW, ALBUQUERQUE, NM 87120

505-659-6125

SUMMARY

Software developer with background in mobile device support and troubleshooting. Proficient with Java for Android development and database management. Experience with individual, group and leadership roles; known for building positive culture and inspiring collaboration through service leadership, effective teamwork, and strong communication skills.

SKILLS

Java	Programmatic Logic	Collaborative Work
GitHub Version Control	Unit Testing	Code Documentation
Android Architecture	Critical & Creative Thinking	Attention to Detail
Relational Databases	Agile Development	Iterative Design

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Deep Dive Coding @ CNM Ingenuity, Albuquerque, NM **Java + Android Development Intern,** Jan 2020 – April 2020

Jan 2020 - April 2020

Learned principles of Object-oriented Programming, including relational database management and Android UI/UX development, and application of Scrum and Agile methods to individual and group projects.

- Choppit Individual project. Implements Jsoup and Regex to parse HTML and extract data to on-device Room database. UI incorporates XML layouts, View Model design, ReactiveX tasks, Data Binding to Recycler Adapters, Android X and Material Design components.
- Scavengr Group project. Managed workflow with Asana and remote collaboration via Slack and GitHub. Uses GMS Vision Library to interpret QR codes. Relies on communication between on-device Room database and remote Apache Derby database on a Spring/Hibernate server via prepared SQL statements to REST Controllers, handled by Okhttp3 and Retrofit 2, with Gson translation.
- Achieved proficiency with IntelliJ IDE and GitHub version control. Developed understanding of Junit5 testing, SQL queries, Gradle and Maven build/dependency systems, and object-oriented programming concepts.

Verizon Wireless, Albuquerque, NM

June 2010 - May 2019

Technical Expert / Coordinator, June 2018 – May 2019

Real time support and training, resolution of escalated customer concerns, and ad-hoc Supervisor duties (see below) as needed.

- Provided coaching and guidance to service reps, turning moments of uncertainty into learning experiences.
- Assisted with troubleshooting, problem-solving, negotiation, and conflict resolution, resulting in a high rate of positive responses on internal satisfaction surveys.
- Resolved escalated customer concerns directly, reaching top rank for Tech Coordinators in 4Q 2018.

 Provided support for teams whose supervisors were out of the office, maintaining motivation and accountability.

Supervisor, June 2017 - May 2018

Supported a team of 12-15 service reps. Drive performance and encourage career growth through training and development. Sustain high team morale and reinforce company culture. Manage schedules, documentation, and shifting priorities with minimal oversight.

- Iteratively designed weekly coaching sessions. Enabled reps moving from unacceptable performance to acceptable, and from acceptable to exceptional.
- Advanced employees' careers by identifying and developing their potential by creating team performance projects and targeted development opportunities.
- Built a healthy, positive, and high-performing team identity in line with company culture through collaboration, communication, and competition. Maintained team morale and cohesion through challenges including announcement of center closure.
- Created solutions to transform bulk reporting data into meaningful knowledge, using proprietary and standard software.
- Workforce management documentation and reports.

Future Leader/Supervisor Point of Contact, June 2016 – May 2017

Learned and implemented skills including team leadership, time management, networking, and resourcefulness.

- Completed 8 weeks of self-guided training and collaborated with tenured Supervisors to observe and practice real world application. I used self-reflection, reporting data, and anonymous surveys to direct my development.
- Developed strategies to encourage positive interactions while redirecting negative attitudes constructively. Demonstrated my values and intent to employees, peers, and superiors. Earned a reputation for easily engaging employees at all levels of tenure and enthusiasm.
- Identified access-restricted applications and created innovative tools using software and physical media to replace critical resources in order to perform Supervisor duties with partial system access. I shared my solutions with my peers.

New Hire/Transition Coach, January 2015 – June 2016

Introduced new employees to job duties and company culture.

- Delivered training in internal systems and call handling techniques. My trainees were able to consistently demonstrate the required skills and knowledge.
- Maximized new hire retention by creating a welcoming learning environment, ensuring strong team morale and fostering open communication. My teams had close to 100% retention through training

Other Positions, June 2010– May 2016

Multiple, overlapping positions: resolution of escalated customer concerns through creative/critical thinking and negotiation; advanced troubleshooting including international service, data devices and ticket escalation; and delivery of consistently positive customer experiences.

EDUCATION

Master of Education (M.Ed), Adult Education and Development, 2018 Strayer University, Online

Bachelor of Arts, English, 2009 Whitman College, Walla Walla, WA

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Network+, ITCAP online certification

A+, ITCAP online certification